this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software developers are you ready it's
time to upgrade your data platform to
inner systems iris choose your language
choose your tools choose your
environment collaborate build faster and
deploy more efficiently when you can
make faster decisions there's no telling
what he'll create ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems comm
slash try to try iris Erin Vonderhaar is
a software developer at no red ink in a
core team member of the Elm programming
language as part of Elm Erin is the
author and maintainer of elde format as
well as the maintainer of elm tests Erin
also hosts the Elm live videocast where
he shares his knowledge and educates
developers about best practices in Elm
prior to no red ink Erin was a developer
and manager at pivotal labs building
full stack web and mobile applications
for a variety of clients Erin thanks for
coming on software engineering radio
it's great to be here thanks for having
me I'm very fascinated by the Elm
programming language it feels like
Haskell and yet it's done on sort of the
front end in the web browser so I'd love
it if you could just give me sort of a
basic introduction to the language and
and how you got involved yeah for sure
I think Elm is kind of known frequently
as we talked about as a functional
language I think we'll touch on some of
the details of that later but kind of
the mission for Elm and what attracted
me to it in the first place when I
started going to some of the Elm meetups
in San Francisco something like five
years ago was that Evan - flicky the
author of Elm is really focused on kind
of the usability of Elm as a language
and specifically has been trying to
design it targeting
developers in a way that brings the
power of functional programming language
and a lot of programming language
research to web developers in a way that
is kind of focused on how web developers
would want to use a programming language
Elm is a programming language and it's
also known as a framework can you tell
us a bit about just the distinctions
between the two yeah sure
so certainly Elm is a language in that
there's a particular syntax for the
files and a particular way you write for
instance lists and expressions and
operators and all that as a framework
Elm also defines I guess what's commonly
called the Elm architecture which is a
particular way of architecting a web app
and what's interesting about Elm is that
that particular architecture for web
apps is essentially a core part of the
language a lot of language features and
features of the compiler are built
around that around that web app
architecture which enables a lot of kind
of niceties of the language that are
targeted at web app developers where a
more general-purpose language might not
have the ability to really optimize the
user experience for a particular type of
developer so I'm kind of being both a
language and a framework specifically
for web app development really helps
simplify the language itself and make it
a lot nicer to use then other languages
that are maybe trying to do a lot more
things and from my experience using Elm
it's been nice to be able to have both
of those things together packaged into
one usable framework combining the two
my sort of introductory question into
all this though is it is 2020 why do we
need a new language what problem is Elm
trying to solve sure well first of all
Elm isn't an especially new language is
starting to become more popular but it
has been around for quite a while I've
been using it for five years it's been
around longer than that so it's kind of
should I say this like solving any
complicated problem particularly well
takes Oh
for something new to come on the scene
and to mature over time I think the the
sweet spot for Elm I think is that
compared to a lot of other options for a
web app development at the time or
currently Elm is very focused on keeping
things simple and kind of zeroing in on
providing just the power and flexibility
that is useful for web app development
without doing a lot of extra unnecessary
stuff for instance a lot of JavaScript
frameworks are limited by what's
available in the language of JavaScript
itself not that that's necessarily a
limitation but Elm being a language
allows it to make choices that give it
more flexibility in what the developer
experience is like then than other
things that just build on top of
JavaScript and you mentioned that the
language has been in development for
quite a while I actually got really
interested in it from the very beginning
I read Evans paper on asynchronous
functional reactive programming for
gooeys back at Harvard and we're gonna
link to that paper in the show notes for
the episode but I'd love to just sort of
I'd love to understand more about each
of those pieces there's a there's a lot
of adjectives about that paper which is
usually the case for academic papers and
just breaking some of those things down
it would be great for you to just give
me an introduction on a few of these
concepts so functional programming
reactive programming I would just love
an introduction of both these of you if
you could provide some color to them
yeah sure and I'll add that I kind of
got introduced to all this at one of
Evans strange loot talks which hopefully
we can add the link to in the show notes
but yeah functional programming that can
be kind of a nebulous term but it tends
to refer to languages that use immutable
data structures that have pure functions
and also that can try to restrict and
have a sophisticated type system that
can kind of represent and/or allow you
to limit when you do risky actions like
do disk IO
something like that reactive programming
is actually a concept that Elm has kind
of moved away from in more recent
versions the reactive programming is
kind of this idea where you define data
sources which is perhaps like you can
think of it as like a stream of values
over time so say you have some entity
that represents a person's name and if
that ever changes
you'll kind of get a new event
propagated through the system based on
that so reactive programming is kind of
this programming model where you build
up essentially a graph of how you
compute the final value for instance how
you compute the page that your user sees
based on a bunch of inputs and a
reactive programming language would kind
of manage updating everything as the
input values change and recomputing only
what's needed to recompute the output
interesting so I actually do remember
seeing one of the releases mentioning in
the release notes that you were moving
away from reactive programming what
spawned that change and what is sort of
replacing it or making it better in the
newer versions of Elm
yeah so the reactive model and this idea
of signals was the data type that
represented it in older versions of Elm
the signals were around up through I
think Elm version 0.16 and my
understanding of what Evan was seeing is
just that it was a very complicated and
unfamiliar way to think about modeling
your web app to have to think in that
reactive programming kind of style so
what's now talked about as the Elm
architecture was basically the new thing
that replaced the reactive programming
aspects of Elm and yeah I mean I'm I'm
pretty convinced as well and I've I've
seen a lot of people who've been trying
to teach Alamo over the years say that
this new model the Elm architecture is a
much simpler thing to be able to
visualize and understand and a better
way to think about what your web app is
doing then the functional reactive
styles at Elm
did in the past you and Evan work
together at no red ink correct yep and
so is that how you adopted Elm at no red
ink did he just introduce it or how did
you how did it get involved in your
production environments oh yeah
so that actually predates me at no red
ink but it also predates oven at no red
ink
Richard Feldman who is one of the
probably most well known speaker on Elm
topics was one of the earliest
developers in narrating and he started
adopting Elm the way that worked was so
we know red ink is an education company
we have a site where teachers can create
grammar and writing assignments and
assign those to students so the way
Richard went about having a red ink
experiment with elm and then eventually
adopted was to take one of the most
complicated pages of our site where we
had a ton of bugs and frequent
regressions which was the assignment
forum where teachers can create new
assignments select from the hundreds of
topics we have and assign them to
classes and to students within classes
so no red inks first use of Elm was to
take just the business logic in
validation logic for that assignment
form page and reimplemented in Elm and
we still had a react site that just
called out to the compiled business
logic in the Elm code and that ended up
being super successful it kind of
quelled the flow of bugs and from there
it's kind of a long process over time
but it was several years ago that we
kind of finished converting almost all
of our site to Elm and basically all of
our new front-end development is all
done in Elm Wow so do you do you guys
have a sense of what the before and
after was like you know from my
experience in introducing these things
in production usually you sort of do
these things on a much lower risk part
of your application because it's a it's
a brand-new language so it's exciting
that he was willing to take that risk on
something that was clearly very
important to the business and to be even
cooler to see do you know if there were
any metrics as to
you know bug rates plummeted or code
readability increase do you have any
sort of case study metrics on on that
initial case yeah well I I believe the
main indicator was kind of just the
number of times day-to-day during a
month that unexpected bugs would come up
it's more of an informal metric at the
time that experiment was happening all
of no red ink was about 20 people so a
very small company and I think there
were maybe four or five engineers at the
time so most of our growth now no red
ink is a hundred people and thirty
engineers and most of our our growth has
been after the adoption of elm and I
mean from that aspect it has not been a
problem and probably we could attribute
a lot of productivity and relatively low
number of like critical production that
bugs on the front end I mean I can't
really think of any that come to mind
but yeah having having the size of
company we have now and the number of
features that we've built over the last
four years
yeah I'm pretty I would be definitely
confident in recommending Elm
as a front-end platform for a company
and you said the entire front end is now
almost completely written in elm so I'm
guessing what happened was Dean the bug
counts dropped and they said great this
sounds like a good company risk to take
we should start to adopt Elm and more
pieces of the code base yep yeah for
sure I think also we know red ink at the
time we were using Elm as kind of an
attractive selling point for hiring
engineers and looking for a particular
type of engineer who's interested in the
the type of like technical excellence
that functional programming is sometimes
associated with and yeah I think that's
still the case today although we haven't
been hiring as aggressively as we used
to but kind of using a fringe or more
fringe language that is exciting and
interesting to people was also I think
part of the reason we were able to
attract a lot of the
great engineers that we have today all
right and I'm sure it's a trade off just
like anything else in the one hand
you've got these people who are more
interested in these fringe languages or
in an alternative way of developing with
more of a craftsman mindset in mind
which is great and then of course that
the turnoff is that it is a more
difficult practice to adopt right out
the gate so you're not necessarily going
to get as many people applying but it's
almost like the right signal you're
looking for which is we don't
necessarily want everyone applying we
want people who understand good
programming practices and want to build
that craftsmanship into their code from
day one and Elna allows you to do that
so in actually diving into those
specific pieces of Elm we know that it
supports strings numbers lists arrays
etc all the basics you would expect out
of a language is there anything common
that's either missing or present that we
take for granted that we should know
about with them sure one of the biggest
things would be Union types or now in
the Elm documentation we call them
custom types which is this was talked
about on a past episode with the author
of the doll language as well
union types are kind of like enums in a
sense where you can list out different
options that can be reserved represented
by a particular type but they also go
beyond enums in that each possible
option is capable of having additional
pieces of data that are specific to that
option for instance we might have a
custom type that represents a user on
our site and that user can either be a
teacher or a student or an administrator
and if the user is a teacher they're
gonna have potentially a premium license
ID and if they're a student they won't
have that piece of information so custom
types allow you to kind of define those
enumerations but also have type safety
around knowing exactly what pieces of
data are available for each option and
which aren't got it so it's more than
just sub classing it's saying for each
of these different configurations there
might be different ways that the objects
are constructed yep exactly
and one of the things the Elm compile
we'll do is make sure that every time
you want to do something with that kind
of object or value as we say you know
that you have to handle each option and
if you ever have an unhandled option
it's gonna be a compile-time error and
elm so that's one of the many ways that
elm helps prevent errors at runtime when
people are first starting to write their
first lines of code in Elm what are they
expecting that they don't end up seeing
coming from say no o P background I
guess if especially if Elm is your first
functional programming language probably
the most unusual thing about it would be
the use of immutable data so that means
for instance if you have some record of
fields that represent some information
and you want to update one of those
fields in JavaScript you'd basically
just replace that field with a new value
you know because it's a pure language is
basically what pure functions mean you
aren't able to manipulate records that
already exist you have to think about
creating new records that represent the
new data that you wanted to have so in
the case of a user where you're updating
their name you'd be returning an entire
new user record with the name having a
new value and everything else being the
same I think that concept is one of the
most unusual you have to think a bit
differently about how to write your
functions that manipulate data but yeah
that's something that's kind of specific
to functional programming languages so I
guess if you're coming from JavaScript
unless you've been really focused on
writing JavaScript in a functional style
that's probably gonna be one of the
biggest new things to get familiar with
that makes sense to be the best example
I could give to JavaScript developers
that's already part of the native
language would be push versus concat so
for example if you're pushing an object
into an array what that's going to do is
it's going to add on a value to that
existing array object and you're
manipulating it in that exact address
space whereas concat is going to look
like it does the exact same thing
because the return
results will be the same but the
difference is it's now allocated to a
different piece of memory so it's almost
like you're creating snapshots in a
window in two previous versions of a
variable when you're doing it immutably
whereas when you can mutate something
you're changing that exact address space
so the way I like to describe it is that
yes the immutability doesn't mean that
you can't have a window into modifying
things it just means that that
modification manifests in new stack
space that you can allocate for a new
variable it just gives you that
flexibility so you can own in a way it's
actually more flexible because you can
look it back at the previous snapshots
without modifying any of those changes
along the way so it's almost like if you
had a debugger and you're looking at how
does this thing evolve over time it's a
lot easier to make that case when you
use immutable objects instead of mutable
ones yep yep exactly that's that's
definitely one of the benefits where
that tends to manifest day to day is
that you kind of have to get familiar
with more of a recursion style of
iterating over things so kind of as an
implication of this Elm doesn't have
constructs like for loops and while
loops instead you have to use recursion
although day to day you tend to not use
a lot of recursion directly but there's
kind of a group of api's that in Elm are
in a much more are in an API style that
is built on recursiveness rather than
loops so for example in Elm you have
lists up map for transforming lists and
lists out folds which a lot of people
know is reduce for kind of processing
lists so because those are kind of the
only options available in a pure
functional language day-to-day you have
to get familiar with those kind of API
is rather than what you're maybe used to
which that's kind of an implication of
this immutable versus mutable difference
recursion and immutability are
definitely foundations of functional
programming another big one is state and
trying to move away from stateless work
can you two
grab more about how statelessness is
important in functional programming and
L sure so the benefits you get from
statelessness
and using only pure functions is that if
you know the inputs to a particular
function you always know what the output
will be so this really helps in defining
reproducible test cases and automated
tests
it also can really help speed up the
debugging process when you're trying to
to debug something that's not working as
expected
you can basically like have a hundred
percent certainty if you've ruled out
one area of the code there's no
unexpected way that something can be
happening there that you didn't think
about like in the case of Ruby where
maybe saw method was dynamically changed
that you didn't realize and it's
affecting your system so those are the
benefits I mean certainly in a web app
there is some kind of state in actuality
like the user is going to be interacting
with your page and things are gonna
happen
as a result of that basically the way it
works in Elm which is also different
from a lot of other functional languages
this is kind of where we get back to Elm
as a framework so Elm as a framework
defines the Elm architecture where
basically the Elm core library is
managing the state for you and you
provide some functions that specify how
the state will be get will update in
response to particular events happening
in your page so basically for your Elm
program you're defining a data type we
call it your model which represents the
current state of your program and then
you're going to define a function called
the update function which takes in an
event and the current state of the
application and returns the new state of
the application that should be the
results of processing that event and
that Elm itself is what takes those two
things and wires them together and
manages updating the Dom in response to
changes and doing the dumb updates
efficiently and managing all that for
you
I'm glad you spoke on the state piece
because for many functional
whether it's closure or in Haskell in
particular even to worry about state you
have to import a particular i/o package
just to deal with something that in many
cases these languages try to avoid as
much as possible but at least you
understand that you are working in the
web and there are some unavoidable
states that you have to manage so the
fact that elm embraces that and
understands that look you want to avoid
state whenever possible but it's
inevitable so here's how to handle it
via the architecture I think that's
super important for the strength of the
language the other thing you touched on
earlier which I wanted to come back to
you was about types you had mentioned
that there was I think was called custom
types or custom sets that describes the
right the custom types that describe
sort of the enumerations plus additional
object validations in talking about
types in a typed language especially in
the front end we often think of
typescript or flow it seems pretty
obvious to me that because this is built
into the language it's stronger than
both of them can you tell me more about
how types are more rigorous in Elm
versus sort of a layer on top framework
like typescript or flow sure so
typescript oh yeah I always get
typescript and pure script confused pure
script has a very sophisticated type
system that must be a great place to be
in by the way where you are so
entrenched in the Elm world you don't
have to worry about things like
typescript right yeah
so hmm I guess the main thing for me
about the types in Elm is that there are
a core part of the language design but
specifically a core part of the language
syntax and that's particularly nice
because it means that the syntax can be
very simple and I think Evans done a
great job of focusing on trying to keep
the syntax of the language as simple as
possible without a bunch of unnecessary
symbols or nesting or weird words that
you don't know what they mean so
specifically compared to some type of
typing system where you're basically
annotating an existing language with
some new special syntax that has to fit
in with the original language
the benefit of being able to have a much
cleaner and much simpler and
straightforward syntax for expressing
type annotations on top of that I'm not
super familiar with the details of the
type system for either flow or
typescript but elm has a very complete
and robust handling of types and in
particular you can do things like
generics maybe that's only a term
familiar to Java developers but being
able to have type annotations where you
have type variables in them and have
that provide type safety basically as
deep as you need it is one of the
specific nice parts of the elm language
I don't actually know how much of those
features are available in some of the
other options yeah the variable piece is
supported in typescript for sure but I
think the key piece you're you're
reflecting on which is important is that
because you're starting from first
principles with the basic language
that's essentially made from scratch the
type system in general has a very simple
grammar in elm because it's built to be
as simple as possible I guess one of the
things I was curious about was in
addition to that is there a plug-in or
library for types for say the HTML DOM
or the jas Dom so for example I know one
of the things you can do in Elm is
JavaScript Interop so is there a whole
type system for the types in JavaScript
or can I interact with a HTML input
element for example in in elm in terms
of a type yeah so the the dom is not
directly interacted with but in the case
of working with data that you're passing
back and forth between JavaScript
basically that there is no difference
between what you're doing in your normal
elm code so when you interact with
JavaScript you use this feature called
ports there's like one or two keywords
in the UM syntax that lets you define
those and you basically use a normal elm
type to specify the type of data that is
going to go through that port and
there's a pretty basic mapping of
how different Elm types map to
JavaScript types and that's just done
automatically there are certain cases
where you may want something more
complicated in JavaScript and be able to
define how that maps to an Elm type so
as a fallback you can always use this
type called JSON value which is an elm
type but it's associated with an API
that lets you essentially define
decoders which specifies how an
arbitrary piece of JSON will map to an
elm type and vice versa
alright so you have built in basically a
JSON parser as well as I mean our port
something like eval where you're
essentially running JavaScript inside of
a elm program I nope it's it's isolated
to be safe and ports are basically more
of our PC mechanism I guess basically
there's two types of ports there's the
incoming ports and outgoing ports and in
both cases the port will have a name and
it'll have a data type that it can sent
so on the outside you will produce these
representations of effects basically you
can you can provide elm a command we
call them or a subscription and it
basically tells the Elm runtime that it
needs to send a particular value out or
expect a certain value to come in and
then on the JavaScript on the JavaScript
side you basically when you start your
elm application you get a handle to the
ports and you can say okay for this
particular port I want to subscribe to
any events coming out of Elm and here's
the callback function to use and to go
the other way on the JavaScript side you
just say okay I want to send this value
to the port with this new okay so if I
wanted to do a data visualization and I
want to interact with d3 is the most
common way of interacting with something
like d3 to use a port in order to
Interop between the two services or what
sort of you know let's say I'm a game
developer
how would I want to handle canvas
development yeah so I think potentially
for canvas and certainly for WebGL there
actually is there are some elm libraries
that wrap those and they're kind of
special libraries because they have
internal access to do things in
JavaScript on your behalf so a few of
the core elm libraries are capable of
doing more sophisticated in their
integrations with JavaScript but if
you're not using one of those things if
there's some JavaScript SDK that you
want to interoperate with then basically
you need to define what kind of values
need to get sent to that API JavaScript
API and what types of values will come
out of it you define elm datatypes for
those and then you just provide your
handlers basically when Elm produces a
value of this type what should the
JavaScript world do with that so yeah
that's certainly the most common for
unusual stuff in the case of d3
specifically tends to have a very large
API and very sophisticated so typically
if you were integrating your own elm app
with d3 you would be doing something
where you'd kind of be defining your own
API of exactly what your elm app wants
to do with with d3 and kind of
implementing a JavaScript API that uses
d3 to do what it wants you'd probably do
something like that as opposed to making
a generic d3 wrapper that exposes the
entire d3 API to Elm okay that makes
sense now taking a step back I sort of
baited with a very complex case with a
sort of integration with a third-party
library that's very robust if we took a
step back to something way more simple
let's say you're building a crud app
what kinds of things are built into the
Elm architecture that we can get right
out of the box so for example when I
think of a web app and thinking of
routing query string manipulation JSON
parsing just sort of run through for me
sort of the basics that you get out of
the box with Elm when you're building a
basic
sure so kind of the first entry point is
when your L map starts you can provide
it some JSON data if you want to you can
also easily integrate with HTTP requests
both making them and then being able to
parse JSON data that comes back through
those that's particularly easy as far as
single page apps and like handling
multiple URLs within the same L map
location that can be done there's some
built-in hooks basically when you define
your own program of how you're going to
update the internal state of your
application when one of those URL change
events happens it's not super high level
so basically you kind of will have to
define your own logic of how you're
handling routing and things like that
but there are there is a URL parser
library for instance that makes it
easier to parse routes but you'll still
have to define the logic of how you're
handling routing and so forth I didn't
realize when I asked that that I wasn't
specifying it was an SP a so I'm guess
I'm curious is elm meant to be run as an
SP a or can you run it as more of a
server-side programming language uh it
can be both well so elm is only for the
front end you can use it now and it's
kind of a new feature I think in Elm
0.18 to be able to use it for building s
pas but you don't have to I think like
90% of no Dinks code is is not s pas and
we've been able to adopt that in certain
cases where it makes sense and it's been
a bit of extra work to set up so I'd say
Elms primary use case still is not
single page apps meaning only one app
per URL but it does have features to
support single page apps if you want to
get more advanced and build that kind of
stuff calling all developers there's no
telling what you can create when you
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris are you ready to build the
applications you want however you want
them are you ready to develop
applications faster than ever
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
in her systems IRS Data Platform ready
set code start coding for free visit
enter systems.com slash try to try iris
in terms of interacting with HTTP and
JSON the Elm way it sounds like instead
of this more SP a routing there you've
got something called subscriptions could
you could you tell me more about those
sure so kind of when you're thinking
about how your Elm app interacts with
the rest of the world whether that's
through HTTP requests or through let's
see what's another good example through
I guess browser events that can happen
there's kind of this boundary between
elm and the rest of the world so there's
two directions and this is it's
basically parallels what we were talking
about with ports you can have incoming
information or events and you can have
outgoing events or actions so the names
for those are now when you want to
trigger something external to happen
those are called commands and when you
want to tell Elm that you want to be
notified when particular things happen
those are called subscriptions so in the
case of subscriptions you don't normally
need those for HTTP requests unless you
want to
for instance monitor the download
progress like the percentage of a
request that's in flight
typically for HTTP requests you only
need to use the outgoing the command
interactions and out or basically you
say okay make this HTTP request when a
response comes back notify me about that
but that doesn't require subscriptions
at all to do that okay so that's the
would that be the recommended way to
handle the external world outside of Elm
instead of sort of filming like SPS or
are there alternatives as well yeah
that's a good question
I think that question kind of goes
beyond the scope of Elm um can support
basically either way you want to go with
that at no red ink we've been well in
the past we used to have our rails
back-end compute some data kind of
packaged it into the HTML the
sent to the front end and then when Elm
starts up we would read some JSON out of
the HTML page and provide that to Elm
when it starts up so that's a model that
works the model we've been switching
more to at no red ink is to have the on
page just load up with nothing
show a loading state and then fire off
an ajax request the elms HTTP module to
load data from various endpoints and
then when that comes back then we
finally display it so that model works
also so yeah pretty much any any
preferred model for your front-end
interacting with your back-end is going
to be supported with them right the
take-home message being you can do
whatever you want and elm can support it
and in whatever way it can shifting
gears just a little bit in terms of
other features that Elm supports one of
the things that I actually got really
interested in with Elm was the fact that
it handles errors really well the error
messages I saw for El mares are some of
the most user friendly and human
readable I've ever seen how did you guys
manage that I'm really curious as to how
you thought so carefully about all the
error message handling in Elm yeah well
that's pretty much all been evans work
and something that he has been
particularly interested in for most if
not all of Elms development when I
started getting into Elm 5 about five
years ago that was one of the things
that I would frequently see I've been
trying to do a tell meetups was to get
Elm in front of new users who had never
seen it before kind of give them the
basic tutorial and then let them play
with it a bit and see what kind of
issues they ran into and look at when
they ran into a problem did the arm
compiler provide something that was
useful and pointed them in the right
direction or did it get them something
confusing or did it tell them something
that was actually sending them in the
wrong direction so it's basically been
through a lot of user observations like
that
and like continued iteration and focus
on on the error messages I know in the
um about nineteen or at least a lot of
the behind-the-scenes work that Evan was
doing was focused specifically on the
error messages and improving the parser
in a way that allowed more information
to be known about the error when it
happened so that it could provide a
better and more helpful error message in
other words if you really care about a
problem and you put in the effort you
can solve it and so in Evans case yeah
he put in a lot of effort to care about
message handling and error handling and
used almost a lot of sort of developer
experience UX to figure out what kinds
of problems are they running into how do
they want to see these errors surface
and that's the part that I was most
excited about for sure yeah and I think
it's I think it can be an easy pitfall
as a technical person who's building a
technical tool to think about only
designing the language for cases where
you have a file that has correct syntax
and works correctly so I think that's an
important thing and something that is a
big reason behind a lot of elam success
I think is that evan has really taken
the time to think about okay what is the
experience when you're an elm user and
you don't yet know what you're doing
well and at the end of the day we're
writing software for other humans to
read so if you provide education
educational material that actually
speaks to humans it's gonna be so much
easier for them to actually find their
problems and remedy them themselves and
if you give some something like Stack
Overflow XYZ did thing that is a very
sort of bland language whereas it almost
feels like when I read error messages in
Elm it's like it's a genie in a bottle
and it's told me something that I'd even
know was a problem and it can provide
suggestions for me which was really
fascinating that it's almost like it
could predict spelling errors or
something like that yeah you know the
way that most people figure out how they
handle their errors in 2020 is they have
the IDE do it for them especially in
JavaScript with vs code it just
development is so much easier because
you sort of get real-time feedback right
in
IDE is there an IDE for elm or can you
integrate it with an existing IDE for
that sort of real-time development yeah
there are a handful of plugins for
different editors specifically the best
one at the moment is the plugin for
IntelliJ which is written by Keith
mizuka that one I think has the most
real-time update and best integration
and has some cool like auto fix features
as well there is an in progress language
server that a handful of folks in the
young community have all been
contributing to and that's ongoing and
still in early stages but that'll
certainly help with support in a lot of
editors but yeah pretty much every
editor out there has at least a basic
plugin for Elm but in general there's
still a lot of room for improvement
there I've actually never heard of a
language server what it what is that all
about that I don't know a ton about it
but it is a protocol I believe started
by Microsoft for Visual Studio code and
it's basically a I guess it's like a
rest protocol in some ways where editors
can talk to a language server for a
particular language like Elm or Ruby or
Haskell and it basically provides a way
for a particular language to create
essentially a back-end for features like
autocomplete jump to definition jump to
documentation features like that in a
way that each editor then won't have to
implement that themselves for every
language instead they can just use this
protocol and the protocol for each
language can be implemented separately
oh wow so it's almost like a centralized
version of storing the entire syntax
tree so you can just sort of reference
all the new language features is that do
I have a rough idea of those that what
that's like yeah yeah I think so and
again I am only vaguely aware of what's
going on but seems like a lot of people
are excited about it and there's a lot
of effort on improving the features for
that
yeah with all these exciting features in
Elma there's a couple of things that
come to mind around sort of like the
meta features that are across all
languages like performance and testing
so starting with performance how does it
compare to JavaScript yeah
so well in one sense some compiles to
JavaScript so you're kind of comparing
this to does compiled Elm for a
particular use perform better than
handwritten JavaScript code or the the
code in whatever framework of your
choosing so there's a lot of things that
Elm does for you that give performance
benefits that you would not want to
write by hand but potentially could get
from some other JavaScript library for
instance we talked about managing the
state of your application earlier
basically every time the state of your
app changes we have two rerender the the
view of the page Elm internally manages
comparing what has changed so it can
find the minimal updates to the dom that
need to be made because dom it dates are
one of the slowest things that are gonna
happen in your web app so that's kind of
a very sophisticated algorithm that is
not something you'd write yourself so in
a lot of cases what you write in Elm is
gonna be faster than what you might
write yourself or very fast compared to
other frameworks
there are several now benchmarks out
there that compare Elm to different
frameworks and it's pretty much always
at or near the top over the past several
years there's a couple fancier more
specialized JavaScript frameworks that
have come out recently they can be it in
certain circumstances but overall like
at no red ink we've never had
performance concerns with elm and in
most cases you're you're not gonna need
more performance than it gives you and
there's there's a few tools you can use
within elm if you're having particular
issues as well how do you do those
performance comparisons when you think
about Elm as a language versus a
framework you sort of mentioned both of
those in there when I went with the way
you just described it to me it sounds
like Elm can be compared similar to
another compile to JavaScript framework
likes
as a language but in terms of as an
architecture or a framework it sounds
like it could also be compared to
reactor view yeah so how are you doing
those performance comparisons if you're
sort of straddling both worlds there
yeah I would say that most people who
use elm are going to use it as a
framework and actually use the owl
runtime to manage a state of a webpage
which rear Enders over time you can
conceivably use Elm for basically just
JavaScript code I guess like I mentioned
when it when they were at Inc was first
investigating Elm we used we used Elm
not as a framework but just as a
language to produce some JavaScript code
that we could call as functions if
you're looking at performance
comparisons for that
I'd say it's basically going to be the
same as JavaScript because it compiles
pretty directly to JavaScript at the
moment there's certainly potential that
in the future Elm layout compiler could
become more sophisticated and do fancier
optimizations but at the moment any any
um code that doesn't deal with actual
web applications and is just functions
it's basically gonna compile pretty
straightforwardly into corresponding
JavaScript under the hood you've got a
lot of those optimizations that you
mentioned earlier but there's also a few
sort of keywords that you've baked into
the language that help increase
performance some of the ones I looked at
were like HTML lazy and HTML keyed how
do those help in increasing performance
for the applications we're developing
yeah both of those things are basically
hints that you can provide to the omron
time so that when it goes to update the
page based on the new state of your
application it can be smarter about how
to do those updates an example would be
say your showing on the page a list of
items if if one of those items moves
it's basically a very difficult problem
for Elm to compare the old state of the
page to the new state of the page
and determine that a particular item
moved from one position to another so
basically in order to stay fast the
default virtual Dom algorithm is just
going to look for some fairly basic
manipulations that might have happened
so if you're writing an app where you're
frequently moving items around in a
large list that's where you can use HTML
keyed and basically the key there means
each item in the list you're giving it
an identifier so that the virtual Dom
diffing algorithm can very quickly
identify which items have changed which
ones have moved around which ones have
been deleted and compute a more optimal
Dom manipulation based on that HTML lazy
is similar in that it's it basically
helps short-circuit some some checks in
the diffing where if you have kind of a
large data structure that it otherwise
would need to traverse all the way
through to compare you can use HTML lazy
and it'll kind of just do some extra
record-keeping to check at a higher
level in your data structure it can it
can more quickly short-circuit and say
okay I know nothing has changed under
here so I don't have to spend the time
checking for other differences
throughout that sub portion of the data
structure two-part question first are
these best practices mentioned in the
docs and further question if not in the
docs do the error messages provide
warnings for these and the reason one of
the things I'm thinking of is something
like keet is very similar to lists in
react oftentimes they suggest that you
should always have a key included for
the mapped object to make do exactly
what Elm is doing and there are warnings
for this if you don't have a key for a
mapped value so I'm wondering if that if
there's documentation on these best
practices or if the if the error
handling actually takes care of this for
you
yeah so this is a situation where there
wouldn't be an error at compile time and
I believe the current version of Elm
doesn't really have any warnings those
are something that I know Elm that Evan
plans to look at in more detail in the
future versions to start adding more
warnings in if they make sense
makes sense I think the way someone
would find about it find out about these
issues at the moment would probably be
running into problems seeing it slow and
then searching for information we have
like the ump community has a discourse
we have a slack channel
there's also Stack Overflow of course
and basically if you go to any of those
places and search for L performance
problems you're gonna basically hear
like hey have you looked at HTML keed
have you looked at HTML lazy and there
is documentation for those but you have
to know what names to look for at the
moment to find the head since Elmo's on
the front end does that mean you would
recommend folks use the dev tools built
in your browser to profile or is there a
profiling tool that you can add as a
plug-in for Elm yeah currently it would
just be through your normal browser dev
tools the stack traces announ are a bit
messy but you can roughly tell which
functions are involved in what's
happening but yeah currently you have to
do that through the existing browser Elm
tools but that's always something that
could improve in the future moving away
from performance another big thing that
people think about when choosing a
language or choosing a framework is
security so how is Elm secure and how
does that compare to JavaScript or
another framework yeah I guess is there
a particular type of security you're
interested or what comes to mind for you
and you all wonder about security for
front-end devs
yeah the two big ones I think about what
for language design in particular you
think about buffer overflows or memory
safety which I would assume would be
pretty well handled given it's a
functional language but then the other
thing too is just in terms of security
vulnerabilities you've got all these
plugins that are part of the LME KO
system you know how are those handled
and can they quickly be addressed yeah
so I'd say maybe the biggest security
feature of elm is in how it handles
external packages that your project
might depend on so specifically for that
the published packages are basically
limited to only peer functions so any
third-party library that's written in
Elm that you want to
you include in your L map it doesn't
have the ability to trigger any kind of
effects like it can't make HTTP requests
unless it has some function that gives
you that request back to you and then
you would actually have to in your
application
tell alum to actually make that request
before it happened
so other packages are very limited in
what they can do to trigger external
events kind of as the nature of them
another thing potentially for security
is that any published packages L
basically enforces semantic versioning
so if there's any changes to an API in a
new version of a package it it's not
gonna break your app because you are
gonna have to explicitly upgrade to the
next major version so you're not going
to accidentally get API breaking API
changes in any of your dependencies
another feature that is paramount to any
languages testing I know one of the
packages you work on is Elm test does
Elm come with test Suites and in sort of
the the the stack of elm testing
granularity when we talk about unit
tests or integration tests or end-to-end
tests for couey's what role does elm
test play and that sort of layer of the
stack so Elm itself has kind of some
basic awareness of the fact that tests
exist and that most projects are going
to have them and so basically you can
define in any um project what additional
libraries are going to be used in your
testing code that are not at all related
to the the production code for that
project beyond that there is an elm
package that provides the API for
writing tests and there's also the elm
test command-line tool that can run the
tests those are the two things that I've
been involved in quite a bit though
there's there's a lot of other people
like Max Goldstein and Noah hall and
Richard Feldman and a lot of other
people more recently who have kind of as
community helps to maintain those Elm
testing tools and is Elm test just
covering unit tests or is it covering
integral
and and like what can you write all of
them with it yeah so there's kind of
some groups of different things so you
can do what most of those so let's start
with unit tests that's probably the
primary focus of the UM test API on top
of that there's also I guess we call it
fuzz testing but quick check or property
testing our words that people might be
familiar with for kind of exhaustively
investigating an entire space of inputs
and outputs to a particular function and
checking invariance against a wide range
of inputs that's another type of testing
that's supported by the UM test library
as for integration testing I actually
have a separate library called elm
program test and its purposes is
basically to simulate the Elm runtime
and the Elm browser and you can write
tests in that for a non program that are
similar to maybe like selenium tests
where you can say okay start up the
program check that this text is on the
page in the heading click this button
simulate this HTTP request coming back
with this JSON data click this other
button select this item from the check
box make sure this is on the page so
that style of testing you can do with my
package on program test it builds on top
of the yum test library and I'd say that
that's kind of the limit of the extent
of types of tests as far as end-to-end
testing there's nothing directly in elm
to do that with and typically you'd want
to exercise your back-end server as well
at the same time so for that type of
testing you'd need some other tool to
write end-to-end tests in I'm just
curious how did you get involved in this
package in particular and are there any
other parts of the language that you're
interested in yeah sure so one of my
previous jobs was at pivotal labs which
has a kind of very specific culture for
doing pair programming all the time and
doing test-driven development in a
certain way so there I was involved with
actually several different
test frameworks the Jasmin test
framework for JavaScript was one that I
worked on a tiny bit while I was there
the robolectric framework for Android
apps I also did a lot of maintenance on
so I've kind of had a long history and
being involved with test frameworks for
various languages so yeah I guess my
involvement in the testing for elm
basically stemmed from wanting to see
more fully featured testing frameworks
available because they just weren't
there five years ago and pretty much
everything we've talked about relating
to testing has all been done in the last
four years or so
Wow so the language has really come
quite a ways in the last only couple of
years what's the future for Elm what are
the next big features you're all are
trying to release so as far as the core
of Elm itself that is pretty much
exclusively Evans
domain he's setting the main roadmap and
does almost all of the work on the core
language however there are a couple
people who've gotten involved recently
doing things like optimization of the
core libraries a few optimizations on
the compiler improving some of the
internal data structures like
dictionaries and lists and things like
that as far as the community the Elm
language server project is a big one
that's going on right now personally
I've been continuing to improve the
program test kind of integration testing
package that I mentioned and also I work
on Elm format which is the source code
formatting tool but I'm looking at
adding some features to that that will
allow people to write kind of more
sophisticated tools that can manipulate
Elm source code or generate Elm source
code things like that so those kind of
fancier tools and hopefully we'll get
some more people interested in improving
a lot of the editor integrations and
things like that
with all these cool new features and
just the language in general being very
robust I just have to be the skeptic
what are the downsides to Elm when are
there use cases when you should not use
Elm yeah so one that comes to
is if you are maybe coming from Haskell
or something like that and are looking
for an extremely powerful type system to
use for front-end code Elam is not
really that it is focused on more of a
user friendly web app mindset oriented
approach to functional programming so if
you're looking for for a very fancy
sophisticated like raking rank n type
system that sort of stuff you'll
probably want to look at something more
like pure script for example let's say
beyond that I guess one downside is the
fact that in the JavaScript world and in
the react world in particular there is a
lot of kind of very sophisticated UI
components that exist as libraries that
you can just pull into your app very
easily Elm doesn't have a ton of that
that's something that's that's still
developing so I'd say that that would be
a potential reason if there's a
particular type of sophisticated UI that
is available in some other framework
that you want to make use of and then on
the flip side are there any particularly
good use cases for starting Elm what's
the best way to get involved to get
started with them yeah so i'm lanie org
it's kind of the starting point there's
also guide elm lang org which is the
basic guidebook for how to get started
kind of goes through all the concepts
that you need to know to get going and
how to set up a project so if you're
interested in learning I would say
that's definitely the place and then
also there's the community page on the
aam website that links to the discourse
or the slack if you're interested in
having a more interactive experience and
hear from people who are in a similar
situation let's see oh yeah as for
adopting it I would say if you're if
you're at an existing company probably
the biggest pitfall you'll have is how
to integrate Elm with whatever build
tools you currently have be that web
pack or I don't even know all the
different options that are popular at
the moment but once you get past that
I'd say it's pretty straightforward
get used to Elm if you are looking for
example at adopting a large framework
like react for instance versus Elm
basically I think of Alma's being kind
of simple and straightforward to the
point that even though it's a totally
new language you can basically pick it
up and get productive in it faster than
you can jump into some existing react
project get familiar with all the
libraries and dependencies that it's
using and come up to speed on that so
yeah I'd say Elm is pretty good fit for
almost all levels of web applications
great and we'll link to documentation as
well as a link to your video list that
you have on YouTube for Elm live for
people to get started with with
programming Elm and the Elm architecture
so with that said is there anything else
that you would like to conclude with
yeah I'd say the YouTube list you just
mentioned was from a couple years ago
and it's something that's been on my
mind this year that kind of start and
Aria reduce some twitch streaming on Elm
and covers some interesting topics so
certainly if anyone's interested in that
kind of stuff shoot me a tweet on
Twitter and I am thinking about getting
that kind of stuff going with some new
content this year great and we'll link
to that playlist as well as your Twitter
and Elms Twitter and all the other
documentation on our show notes Erin
thanks again for coming on software
engineering radio oh yeah thanks so much
for your time and putting this together
developers take your marks it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris it's time to deliver
complex mission-critical applications in
the fastest route possible it's time to
use any data from any source it's time
to embed analytics and create
interactive user interfaces so what are
you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner systems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications ready
set code start coding for free
visit inner systems.com slash tried to
try iris thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening
[Music]